A Guide to the Papers of the North American Land Company 1794-1804
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the North American Land Company 1794-1805
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8146-a
This collection consists of 26 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased on 8 May 1984.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist of business correspondence and documents of Sylvanus Bourne, consul general of the United States in Holland and an agent for Dutch investors in the company. The letters chiefly concern property in Washington City conveyed to Daniel Crommelin and Sons, Amsterdam, by Greenleaf, and efforts by the firm to secure the property. Of interest are letters of Morris re: the company's books and judgments against him. The British blockade of Dutch ports in 1799, slow tobacco sales in Holland, and honors paid by the Dutch to the memory of George Washington are also mentioned. Correspondents include Edward Tilghman, Tobias Lear, Thomas Browne, and the banking firm of Rocquette, Elzevier, and Beeldemaker, Rotterdam.
Contents List
- Printed proposal of a loan to James Greenleaf of New York from Dutch bankers, Rocquette, Elzevier, and Beeldemaker, Rotterdam 1794, D
- John Gannt certifying the recording of a Deed Poll conveying land from James Greenleaf to Peter Godefray, Rutger Jan Schimmel-pennick and Robert Crommelin. Signed by Secretary of State Edmund Randolph 1794 Sep 20, ALS
- James Greenleaf to Sylvanus Bourne 1795 Jan 2, ALS
- Draft of a bond for Morris, Nicholson, and Greenleaf to Daniel Crommelin and Sons, Amsterdam 1796 Mar 11, ADS
- J. Beeldemaker to Sylvanus Bourne 1796 Jul 29, ALS
- Promissory note signed by James Greenleaf and Protest of Note issued to Edward Fox 1796 Aug 5 and 1797 Apr 10, ADS
- Account of Sylvanus Bourne to Daniel Crommelin and Sons, Amsterdam 1796 Dec - 1800 Mar, AD
- G.C.T. Reyman to Sylvanus Bourne 1797 Feb 20, ALS
- Daniel Crommelin and Sons to Sylvanus Bourne 1797 Feb 23, ALS
- A.C.E. Greenleaf to Sylvanus Bourne 1797 Mar 24, ALS
- Robert Morris to Edward Tilghman 1797 Aug 25, ALS
- Edward Tilghman to Robert Morris 1797 Aug 28, ALS
- Assignees of Morris, Greenleaf, and Nicholson to Sylvanus Bourne 1797 Sep 23, AL
- Sylvanus Bourne to Tobias Lear 1798 Nov 10, ALS
- Robert Morris to Garret Cottringer 1799 Jan 5, ALS
- Thoman Browne to Sylvanus Bourne 1799 Dec 15, ALS
- Thoman Browne to Sylvanus Bourne 1799 Dec 18, ALS
- Sylvanus Bourne to Tobias Lear 1800 Apr 4, ALS
- A.C.E. Greenleaf to her brother 1800 May 16, ALS
- Charlotte Scholten to Sylvanus Bourne [1800?] May 22, ALS
- Tannui Scholten to Sylvanus Bourne 1800 [May] 22, ALS
- Rocquette and Beeldemaker to Sylvanus Bourne 1800 Aug 3, ALS
- James Greenleaf to Sylvanus Bourne 1802 Dec 18, ALS
- Daniel Crommelin and Sons to Sylvanus Bourne 1803 Feb 14, ALS
- Printed Plan for participation in a new loan, involving Hope and Company, R. and Th. de Smet H. and Wm. and J. Willink 1804 Jan 1, D
- Daniel Crommelin and Sons to Sylvanus Bourne 1805 Jan 19, ALS